Guide to the photograph album: Scenes of Egypt During WWI AD.MC.015
Akkasah: Photography Archive (NYU Abu Dhabi)
Scenes of Egypt During WWI
1916-1919
Akkasah: Photography Archive (NYU Abu Dhabi)
Antiquariat Inlibris (1883-present)
AD.MC.015
1 Linear Feet - One oblong album (18.5 × 22 cm) with 72 photographs. The photographs measure approximately 8 × 5 cm.
One oblong album (18.5 × 22 cm) with 72 photographs, mostly sepia, neatly ensconced behind window mounts and many of them captioned at the back. 12 ff. The photographs measure approximately 8 × 5 cm. Brown cloth string-tied boards.
This photograph album contains photographs of scenes captured first-hand in Egypt and Palestine by an unidentified Royal Flying Corps aviator in 1916–1919. At least for a time, he was stationed near Cairo, quite possibly assigned to the Number 14 Squadron that assisted T. E. Lawrence in the Arab Revolt (1916–18). This photograph album shows glimpses of life in Egypt during wartime, particularly in Cairo and Alexandria and includes a few images from Jerusalem, Bethlehem, and Jaffa in Palestine. A heavy gun on large wheels and surrounded by a sandbag wall, situated at Aboukir according to the caption verso of image, suggests this as the pilot's base. Included in this album are 4 photographs taken of the demonstrations in Alexandria during the Egyptian Revolution of 1919. Other views of Alexandria include the Boulevard Ramleh, street scenes with more horse drawn carts and trains at the Alexandria Station. A scant few scenes pertain to the war, showing two types of aircraft, sandbag barricades, a large army truck and artillery.
Box 015
Arrangement
The collection was processed as it was received.
Biographical / Historical
This photograph album contains photographs of scenes captured first-hand in Egypt and Palestine by an unidentified Royal Flying Corps aviator in 1916–1919. At least for a time, he was stationed near Cairo, quite possibly assigned to the Number 14 Squadron that assisted T. E. Lawrence in the Arab Revolt (1916–18).
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions at akkasah.org. For access to physical album contact Akkasah Center for Photography, akkasah@nyu.edu +971 2628 5531
Scope and Contents
This photograph album shows glimpses of life in Egypt during wartime, particularly in Cairo, Alexandria, and desolate regions in between, skillfully captured by a British aviator who seems to have been especially curious of the elusive women in burqas. He includes several lovely photographs of the people in traditional costume and going about their usual routines, in Egypt, and a scant few from Jerusalem, Bethlehem, and Jaffa in Palestine. Camel caravans and windmills pierce the desert regions, and a charming mud village flanks the bank of an irrigation canal. A heavy gun on large wheels and surrounded by a sandbag wall, situated at Aboukir according to the caption verso of image, suggests this as the pilot's base. Photographs of Cairo include the Saladin Citadel with the Mosque of Muhammad Ali towering from the summit, city streets mostly with only one motorcar; otherwise all foot traffic and horse-drawn carriages. Included in this album are 4 very scarce snapshot photographs taken of the riots in Alexandria during the Egyptian Revolution of 1919. Other views of Alexandria include the Boulevard Ramleh, street scenes with more horse drawn carts and trains at the Alexandria Station. A scant few scenes pertain to the war, showing two types of aircraft, sandbag barricades, a large army truck and artillery.
Custodial History
Akkasah, the Center for Photography at NYU Abu Dhabi, acquired the collection in December 2015.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Album purchased from Antiquariat INLIBRIS, Rathausstraße 19, 1010 Wien, Austria in 2015.
Photographic Prints; Gelatin Silver Prints; Egypt; Air Force; Military/Soldiers; Jerusalem; Alexandria, Egypt; Regional/National Dress; Antiquariat Inlibris (1883-present)
- The front cover of the album 'Scenes of Egypt During WWI'., Circa 1916-1919; nyuad_pa000003_afr01; 1 Photographic Prints (Box 015)
  Egypt; English Writing
- The inside front cover of the album 'Scenes of Egypt During WWI', part of the "happy records" series, produced by J. W. & Co, Ltd, London., Circa 1916-1919; nyuad_pa000003_afr02; 1 Photographic Prints (Box 015)
- Three coastal scenes, including people walking on a pier., 1917; nyuad_pa000003_n000001; 1 Photographic Prints (Box 015)
  Coast; Beaches; Water; Boats/Ships; Transportation; Docks/Piers/Jetties; Men; Women; Flags; Group Portraits; Landscapes; Photographic Prints; Gelatin Silver Prints; Montaza, Alexandria, Egypt; Tents
- From left-hand clockwise: A tree lined walkway, a grotto at Montaza convalascent hospital, and a coastline., 1917; nyuad_pa000003_n000002; 1 Photographic Prints (Box 015)
  Hospitals; Beaches; Water; Landscapes; Gelatin Silver Prints; Montaza, Alexandria, Egypt; Photographic Prints; Forest/Woodlands; Coast; Gardens; Sanitariums/Sanatoriums
- From top left clockwise: People walking in Roset Gardens, ostriches and pelicans., Circa 1916-1919; nyuad_pa000003_n000003; 1 Photographic Prints (Box 015)
  Birds; Animals; Gardens; Lakes; Rivers; Water; Men; Women; Group Portraits; Zoos; Photographic Prints; Gelatin Silver Prints; Alexandria, Egypt
- From left clockwise: A group walking through some gardens, a zebra in Nozha Gardens, and a building set amongst formal gardens., Circa 1916-1919; nyuad_pa000003_n000004; 1 Photographic Prints (Box 015)
  Men; Women; Fez/Tarboush; Regional/National Dress; Head Covers/Veils; Group Portraits; Streets/Roads; Animals; Gardens; Buildings; Alexandria, Egypt; Photographic Prints; Gelatin Silver Prints; Zoos; Niqab/Burqa; Hats
- From top left clockwise: The Antonaides Gardens, a city landscape, and people on a street in Ramleh., Circa 1916-1919; nyuad_pa000003_n000005; 1 Photographic Prints (Box 015)
  Gardens; Palm Trees; Streets/Roads; Men; Buildings; Group Portraits; Landscapes; Alexandria, Egypt; Shops; Photographic Prints; Gelatin Silver Prints; Street Lamps
- From left clockwise: A tomb in the Greek Cemetery of Alexandria, people riding on a carriage, and a village., Circa 1916-1919; nyuad_pa000003_n000006; 1 Photographic Prints (Box 015)
  Men; Women; Group Portraits; Head Covers/Veils; Carriages/Coaches; Transportation; Horses; Animals; Streets/Roads; Monuments/Memorials; Buildings; Cemeteries; Tombs/Mausoleums; Alexandria, Egypt; Photographic Prints; Gelatin Silver Prints
- From top left clockwise: A portrait of men, women, and children; a donkey working a water wheel; and a portrait of two women., Circa 1916-1919; nyuad_pa000003_n000007; 1 Photographic Prints (Box 015)
  Women; Girls; Children; Boys; Head Covers/Veils; Men; Fez/Tarboush; Agriculture/Farms; Donkeys; Deserts; Palm Trees; Photographic Prints; Gelatin Silver Prints; Egypt; Group Portraits; Regional/National Dress; Hats
- Three portraits of men, women, and children., Circa 1916-1919; nyuad_pa000003_n000008; 1 Photographic Prints (Box 015)
  Women; Head Covers/Veils; Individual Portraits; Boys; Children; Group Portraits; Men; Street Lamps; Egypt; Jewelry; Photographic Prints; Gelatin Silver Prints; Regional/National Dress; Niqab/Burqa; Turbans
- From top left clockwise: A woman riding a water buffalo, a woman carrying a jog on her head, and women and men by the edge of a body of water (canal between Alexandria and Cairo)., Circa 1916-1919; nyuad_pa000003_n000009; 1 Photographic Prints (Box 015)
  Women; Head Covers/Veils; Cattle/Cows; Animals; Water; Architecture; Children; Men; Photographic Prints; Gelatin Silver Prints; Group Portraits; Individual Portraits; Streets/Roads; Canals; Egypt; Pottery; Niqab/Burqa
- From left clockwise: People gathered outside the Mosque of Sidi Gaber, Alexandria tram station, and a body of water., Circa 1916-1919; nyuad_pa000003_n000010; 1 Photographic Prints (Box 015)
  Boys; Girls; Children; Mosques; Religious Sites; Group Portraits; Water; Head Covers/Veils; Alexandria, Egypt; Trains; Railways; Transportation; Men; Photographic Prints; Gelatin Silver Prints
- From left clockwise: People standing in front of mud brick buildings, a woman standing in some gardens, and men working at a quarry., Circa 1916-1919; nyuad_pa000003_n000011; 1 Photographic Prints (Box 015)
  Architecture; Men; Women; Streets/Roads; Railways; Transportation; Group Portraits; Quarry/Mine; Individual Portraits; Head Covers/Veils; Egypt; Photographic Prints; Gelatin Silver Prints; Workers; Buildings; Niqab/Burqa
- From left clockwise: Cars and carriages in front of a building, the Cairo citadel and Mohamed Ali Mosque, and the Sultan Hassan Mosque., Circa 1916-1919; nyuad_pa000003_n000012; 1 Photographic Prints (Box 015)
  Architecture; Cars/Trucks; Transportation; Carriages/Coaches; Mosques; Religious Sites; Cairo, Egypt; Mosque-Madrassa of Sultan Hassan; Mosque of Muhammad Ali Pasha; Forts/Castles; Horses; Street Lamps; Animals; Men; Photographic Prints; Gelatin Silver Prints
- From top left clockwise: A man rides a horse and cart in front of Kasr el Nil Bridge, a street with a Nicolas Soussa Frères shop, and a street scene., 1917; nyuad_pa000003_n000013; 1 Photographic Prints (Box 015)
  Cigarettes; Shops; Cairo, Egypt; Restaurants/bars; Street Lamps; Streets/Roads; Bridges; Horses; Carriages/Coaches; Men; Fez/Tarboush; Transportation; Individual Portraits; Group Portraits; Photographic Prints; Gelatin Silver Prints; Statues/Sculptures; Hats
- From left clockwise: A procession including a camel, airmen standing next to a Bristol F.2 Fighter, and two men in a boat., Circa 1916-1919; nyuad_pa000003_n000014; 1 Photographic Prints (Box 015)
  Military/Soldiers; Air Force; Uniforms; Airplanes; Parades/Processions; Camels; Animals; Egypt; Boats/Ships; Lakes; Transportation; Water; Men; Crowds; Group Portraits; Photographic Prints; Gelatin Silver Prints
- From top left clockwise: A view of Zabadani, Syria; the interior of Al Aqsa Mosque; and a group portrait of men and children., Circa 1916-1919; nyuad_pa000003_n000015; 1 Photographic Prints (Box 015)
  Syria; Jerusalem; Palestine; Regional/National Dress; Mosques; Religious Sites; Postcards; Gelatin Silver Prints; Photographic Prints; English Writing; Children; Boys; Men; Group Portraits; Mountains/Hills; Architecture; Landscapes; Turbans
- From left clockwise: The Arch of Ecce Homo; a landscape view of Jaffa, and a panorama of the coast of Jaffa., Circa 1916-1919; nyuad_pa000003_n000016; 1 Photographic Prints (Box 015)
  Jerusalem; Jaffa; Palestine; English Writing; Streets/Roads; Palm Trees; Boats/Ships; Transportation; Water; Coast; Men; Women; Head Covers/Veils; Group Portraits; Photographic Prints; Gelatin Silver Prints
- From top left clockwise: A view of Bethlehem, the interior of a church, and a view of Nazareth., Circa 1916-1919; nyuad_pa000003_n000017; 1 Photographic Prints (Box 015)
  Nazareth; Bethlehem; Churches; Religious Sites; Religious Crosses; Buildings; Architecture; Photographic Prints; English Writing; Gelatin Silver Prints; Palestine; Mountains/Hills
- From left clockwise: People on a boat in the Jordan River, the Garden of Gethsemane, and Gehenna., Circa 1916-1919; nyuad_pa000003_n000018; 1 Photographic Prints (Box 015)
  Jordan River; Rivers; English Writing; Gethsemane, Jerusalem; Gehenna/Valley of Hinnom; Water; Boats/Ships; Transportation; Men; Group Portraits; Palestine; Religious Sites; Photographic Prints; Gelatin Silver Prints; Landscapes; Mountains/Hills
- From top left clockwise: (No. 138) General Allenby in Jerusalem, a view of Jerusalem, and (no. 163) soldiers in front of the Dome of the Rock., Circa 1916-1919; nyuad_pa000003_n000019; 1 Photographic Prints (Box 015)
  Dome of the Rock/Qubbat al-Sakhrah; Mosques; Religious Sites; Jerusalem; Officials; Horses; Animals; Postcards; Photographic Prints; Gelatin Silver Prints; English Writing; Military/Soldiers; Men; Uniforms; Individual Portraits; Buildings; Palestine; Temple Mount/al-Ḥaram al-Šarīf; Allenby, Edmund Henry Hynman, Viscount, 1861-1936
- Three views of demonstrations in Alexandria., March-April 1919; nyuad_pa000003_n000020; 1 Photographic Prints (Box 015)
  Men; Crowds; Signs/Signposts; Alexandria, Egypt; Buildings; Group Portraits; Streets/Roads; Photographic Prints; Gelatin Silver Prints; Flags; Politics; Democracy; Demonstrations/Protests
- From top left clockwise: A crowd demonstrating and a man walking beside a military vehicle in Alexandria, and an aerial view of Jerusalem., March 1919; nyuad_pa000003_n000021; 1 Photographic Prints (Box 015)
  Crowds; Military/Soldiers; Umbrellas/Parasols; Flags; Alexandria, Egypt; Palestine; Buildings; Cars/Trucks; Transportation; Group Portraits; Men; Streets/Roads; Photographic Prints; Gelatin Silver Prints; Women; Jerusalem; Democracy; Demonstrations/Protests
- From left clockwise: A person standing in front of a palm tree, soldiers sitting near sandbags, and a soldier holding a gun., Circa 1916-1919; nyuad_pa000003_n000022; 1 Photographic Prints (Box 015)
  Abu Qir, Egypt; Guns; Uniforms; Military/Soldiers; Weapons; Palm Trees; Boys; Children; Men; Individual Portraits; Cars/Trucks; Transportation; Photographic Prints; Gelatin Silver Prints; Group Portraits; Streets/Roads; Cannons
- From top left clockwise: A soldier standing next to a gun in Fort Tawfiq, Aboukir; a man in front of a windmill, and soldiers near a biplane., Circa 1916-1919; nyuad_pa000003_n000023; 1 Photographic Prints (Box 015)
  Forts/Castles; Men; Uniforms; Military/Soldiers; Airplanes; Transportation; Individual Portraits; Group Portraits; Deserts; Photographic Prints; Gelatin Silver Prints; Architecture; Egypt; Agriculture/Farms; Medals/Insignia
- From left clockwise: A portrait of a man and woman (1917), men standing with camels, and a village in Minia (1916)., nyuad_pa000003_n000024; 1 Photographic Prints (Box 015)
  Men; Women; Facial Hair; Fez/Tarboush; Head Covers/Veils; Photographic Prints; Group Portraits; Regional/National Dress; Minia, Egypt; Egypt; Palm Trees; Camels; Transportation; Animals; Gelatin Silver Prints; Niqab/Burqa; Hats
- The inside back cover of the album 'Scenes of Egypt During WWI'., Circa 1916-1919; nyuad_pa000003_zbk01; 1 Photographic Prints (Box 015)
  Egypt
- The back cover of the album 'Scenes of Egypt During WWI'., Circa 1916-1919; nyuad_pa000003_zbk02; 1 Photographic Prints (Box 015)